Let’s move now to protection domains
We said that for building a trusted system,
we need to have a clear understanding of what
can be done and who can do it. We can ask
ourselves: what does it mean to have a clear
understanding of what can be done and who
can do it?
To answer such a question, we can note that
each system is composed of a set of objects
(could be both hardware and software).
Each object can be manipulated through a set
of operations, and such operations can take
place within the execution of processes.
A domain is a set of  pairs
that refer to one user or a group of users.
According to the Principle of Least Authority,
security works best when each domain has the
minimum objects/privileges required to perform
a certain task.
Here we have an example with three domains,
each containing some objects and associated
operations. As you can see, the same object
(File 1 for instance) can be associated with
different domains and with different operations.
At the same time, the same object (Printer
1) can also exist with the same operation
for multiple domains.
We assume that each process is executed in
one protection domain and that the operating
system could allow the process to switch between
domains. In Unix, the domain of a process
is given by the user id and the group id of
the user that is currently logged in and running
such a process.
If we now focus our attention on how to maintain
the information about various domains, we
realize we need to maintain a matrix like
the one shown in these figures (the one at
the bottom is an extension on the one on the
top with domain-switching permissions too).
In practice, such a matrix would be sparse
(most cells are empty), and storing it as
a matrix is not efficient, we can go for either
rows or columns. If we store information per
column , we are then referring to Access Control
Lists. If we do it per-row , we are referring
to Capabilities. We will cover both in the
following videos.